Guide to the Property agreements, Washington, DC, 1809-1835 MS2090
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Property agreements, Washington, DC
1809-1835
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2090
2 Linear Feet
Collection consists of 48 indentures, or property agreements. These documents date from 1809-35. Most of the documents have the term "indenture" appearing in the first sentence, although they are variously described by city officials in the agreements themselves as deeds, bills of sale, leases, and agreements.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by George Washington University sometime late in 1983 or early in 1984.
Historical or Biographical Note
The clerk of the circuit court for Washington County in the District of Columbia was required by a law of March 3, 1801 to record deeds. In these early years the clerk's office included the office for the recording of deeds. On July 17, 1805 William Brent became clerk of the circuit court,'a position which he held for 38 years. Unless otherwise specified, all these agreements are signed at the end by William Brent, clerk, and the date he received them is present:. along with exact citations to the Liber of the land records of Washington County in the District of Columbia where the transactions were then also recorded.
Many of those involved in these agreements were prominent figures. Those who signed in their official capacity, for instance those who were justices of the peace, were also pillars of the community. Many of these names are the same as those who were buying and selling.
Not all these transactions cover real estate exchanges between the leading citizens of the community. Some cover slave sales; sale of a dwelling to a freeman of color; the sale of the contents of a printing shop; and a pre-marital agreement.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of 48 indentures, or property agreements. These documents date from 1809-35. Most of the documents have the term "indenture" appearing in the first sentence, although they are variously described by city officials in the agreements themselves as deeds, bills of sale, leases, and agreements. They contain the required signatures of the partners to the agreements and of city officials such as justices of peace and the clerk of the circuit court, but only two of them have any seals. In other cases circles are drawn for the placement of seals, but they are not present.
These agreements concern property of several types: real estate, household goods, chattel and slaves. They dating and signing by William Brent is the one element common to all pieces in the collection; this recording was the last step for property transactions; the clerk's date was always the latest one found on each agreement.
Each listing includes the date when recorded by Brent, the name of the seller and then the buyer, the type of agreement, and the lot and square numbers if mentioned. During the time of these agreements, the District of Columbia was comprised of Washington County and Alexandria County; Washington County included Washington City and Georgetown. Please bear in mind that for the most part land in Georgetown and in the various additions to Georgetown was designated by lot numbers whereas land in Washington City was designated by square and lot numbers.
The spelling of names varies even within the same indenture. For the most part the spelling and version of the name used here is that which appeared in the section appearing before Brent's signature.
Collection note
From original finding aid: when this collection was processed, each piece was opened and encapsulated in mylar and then individually numbered on a label which had been affixed to the mylar.
Antenuptial contracts; Slaves; Washington (D.C.); Deeds -- Washington, DC; Indentured servants -- Washington (D.C.); Real property; Slavery; Washington (D.C.) -- History; Brent, William; District of Columbia. Office of the Recorder of Deeds; United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)
- Deed: Alexander Robert Beall to Samuel Beall, 1809 November 09 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  [From original finding aid]: Tract of land called "James's Gift". Lacks section for clerk of circuit court. Acknowledged by William Cranch as chief judge of the circuit court of the District of Columbia
- Deed: Joseph Garner to William Stewart, 1810 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  [From original finding aid]: Land on Jefferson St. in Georgetown
- Deed: Richard Parrot to Thomas Beall, 1810 May 01 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  [From original finding aid]: Part of tract of land originally called "Rock of Dumbarton"
- Bill of sale: Levin Soper to George McCalley, 1810 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  [From original finding aid]: for slave
- Deed: Thomas B. Beall to Elisha Lanham, 1810 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  [From original finding aid]: Lots 173 and 174 in Beall's first addition to Georgetown
- Deed: Joseph Huddleston to David Sommerville, 1810 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 3 in square 461. Lacks section for clerk of circuit court. Acknowledged by B. Thruston as assistant judge of the circuit court of the District of Columbia
- Deed: George Schnaetzete to Abner Ritchie., 1810 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 149 in Beatty and Hawkins addition to Georgetown
- Deed: Thomas Beall to Nathaniel Heath, 1810 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  [From original finding aid]: Lots 211 and 212 in Beall's second addition to Georgetown
- Deed: George Magruder to William Steuart,'Samuel Turner, Jr., and Patrick Magruder, 1810 November 05 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  [From original finding aid]: Lots 19 and 20 in Georgetown
- Release of mortgage: John P. Van Ness to William Hammond Dorsey, 1810 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Deed: William H. Dorsey to John Herford, 1810 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 4 a&b in square 380. Lacks signature in section for clerk of circuit court
- Deed: William H. Dorsey to John Herford, 1811 May 09 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Deed:John Simpson to Thomas James Mudd, 1811 October 08 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  [From original finding aid]: [Lot 7] Beatty and Hawkins and.Bealls's additions to Georgetown
- Deed: James Dunlop to Rev. William Matthews, 1814 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 11 in square 376
- Deed: John Murdoch to William H. Dorsey, 1814 May 09 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 11 in City of Washington
- Deed: John Murdoch to William H. Dorsey, 1815 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Stephen B. Balch to Peter Coulter, 1816 January 03 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  [From original finding aid]: Deed: Lot 254 in Beatty and Hawkins addition to Georgetown
- Deed: Thomas Law to Thomas Claxton, 1816 May 01 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 5 in square 690
- Bill of sale: Richard Young to Joseph Gales, Jr., 1816 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  [From original finding aid]: for horses and coach
- John and Marcia Van Ness to Thomas Hillard, 1816 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  [From original finding aid]: Lease. Lot 9 in square 293
- Deed: Joseph Gales, Jr. to George Andrews, 1816 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 9 in square 407
- Deed: Thomas Law to Simon Meade, 1816 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  [From original finding aid]: Square 408
- Bill of sale: Perrin Willis to J. P. Van Ness, William Brent, and R. C. Weightman, 1816 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  [From original finding aid]: of tenement on Pennsylvania Avenue
- Deed: Richard Parrott to Leonard Mackall, 1817 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  [From original finding aid]: Property known as "Pretty Prospects"
- Lease: Samuel Hoot to Samuel Hutchinson, 1817 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 3 in square 320
- Bill of sale: Joel K. Mead to Romolus Riggs, 1817 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  [From original finding aid]: of printing shop contents
- Joel K. Mead to Romolus Riggs, 1818 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  [From original finding aid]: Bill of sale of printing shop contents
- Richard Bland Lee Jun. & William W. Seaton, 1823 January 17 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  [From original finding aid]: Agreement concerning a mulatto slave.304 17 F 1823. Harriet Greene to Charles Cutts. Deed. Part of lot 1 in square 575
- Deed: Mary Burns to George Watterston., 1823 March 13 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 3 in square 762 and lot 8 in square 845
- Bill of sale: Waring B. Beall to Otho B. Beall, 1823 March 25 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 18 in square 163 plus slave and household goods
- Deed: Walter Smoot and Ulysses Ward to Walter Ringgold. a&b, 1823 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  [From original finding aid]: Lots 163 and 164 in Beatty and Hawkins addition to Georgetown
- Bill of sale: Miriam Ball to Sarah P. Bowling, 1823 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  [From original finding aid]: Slaves and some household goods
- Deed: William Archer to James Hoban, 1823 June 06 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 18 in square 8
- Deed: Nathaniel Kelly to James Kennedy., 1823 June 09 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 43 in old Georgetown
- Bill of sale: John Rumney to James Curren, 1823 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  [From original finding aid]: A dwelling in square 54; to a freeman of colour
- Bill of sale: James Semmes to John Threlkeld, 1823 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  [From original finding aid]: Goods and chattels
- Deed of conveyance: Rebecca and John Ford to Elizabeth Threlkeld, 1823 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 114 in Threlkeld's addition to Georgetown
- Deed: Walter J. Chandler to Gustavus Beall, 1823 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 10 in square 172
- Deed: Tench Ringgold to Ignatius Clarke., 1823 June 21 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  [From original finding aid]: Ringgold as Marshal seized house and lot in parts of lots 14 and 15 in Beall's addition to Georgetown. This was the property of Thomas Mudd and was sold at auction
- Deed: Charles Glover to Ignatius Mudd, 1823 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  [From original finding aid]: Lot 10 in square 258 and lots 2 and 3 in square 1045. This is the only indenture done on a preprinted form
- Deed: Peter Lenox to Frederick Keller, 1826 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  [From original finding aid]: Lots 26, north half of 27, in square 327
- Bill of sale: Joseph Wood to Anthony Hoimead, 1826 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  [From original finding aid]: Household goods
- Deed: Peter J. Maitland to Richard Peters (both of Philadelphia)., 1830 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  [From original finding aid]: Parts of lots 13 and 14 in square 490. This indenture has a seal on it
- Deed: Richard Peters to Peter J. Maitland (both of Philadelphia), 1830 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  [From original finding aid]: Parts of lots 13 and 14 in square 490. This indenture has a seal'on it
- Marriage contract: George A. Smoot and Mrs. Ann Mitchell, 1833 July 13 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  [From original finding aid]: She is to occupy, possess and enjoy all real and personal property in her possession free from his claims and vice versa
- Lease: John P. Van Ness to James Hoban, 1835 August 11 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  [From original finding aid]: Part of lot 3 in square 491
- Bill of sale: George Dashiell to Joseph Milligan, 1811 November 30 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  [From original finding aid]: for goods and chattels (including a slave)